A Finding Aid to the Abraham Rattner and Esther Gentle Papers, 1891-1986, in the Archives of American Art AAA.rattabra
Archives of American Art
- Writings, 1940-1972, undated; Series 8; (box 9; 0.9 linear ft.)
  - "Science of Mind,", 1947, undated (Box 9, Reel 5268)
  - Personal memories, 1947 (Box 9, Reel 5268)
  - "We Remember Bettina Stories,", 1947 (Box 9, Reel 5268)
  - Writings on Bettina Bedwell, 1948 (Box 9, Reel 5268)
  - Lecture notes, 1948-1949, undated (Box 9, Reel 5268)
  - "The Artist and Our Society,", 1949; (2 folders) (Box 9, Reel 5268)
  - "The Artist Makes His Statement," Woodstock paper, 1950 (Box 9, Reel 5268)
  - Miscellaneous, 1958 (Box 9, Reel 5268)
  - "Out of the Darkness Came the Light,", [1959] (Box 9, Reel 5268)
  - "Notes to Myself,", 1960s-1970s (Box 9, Reel 5268)
  - "As A Day Ends,", 1971-1972 (Box 9, Reel 5268)
  - Fragments, undated; (2 folders) (Box 9, Reel 5268)
  - Thoughts on painting used for the Allen Leepa book, undated (Box 9, Reel 5268)
  - Text for a Henry Miller portfolio, undated (Box 9, Reel 5268)
  - Poem, The Invisible City, undated (Box 9, Reel 5268)
  - "The Schism Between the Artist and Society,", undated (Box 9, Reel 5268)
  - "Technical Problems in Painting,", undated (Box 9, Reel 5268)
  - Thoughts on painting and art, undated; (2 folders) (Box 9, Reel 5268)
  - "The Super Sensible Nature of Man,", undated; (11 folders) (Box 9, Reel 5268-5269)
  - Notebooks of various writings, annotated typescript, undated; (3 folders) (Box 9, Reel 5269)
  - Miscellaneous writings, 1949, 1960, undated; (4 folders) (Box 9, Reel 5269)
- Studio Notebooks, 1935-1975, undated; Series 9; (boxes 10-11; 1.9 linear ft.)
  This series has been divided into notebooks numbered by Rattner and those arranged chronologically. All of the notebooks remain in their original order. Rattner used these notebooks to keep track of his paintings, their titles, when they were painted, what gallery he sent them to and when, where and when they were exhibited, what medium he used, or what person he gave them to as gifts.
  9.1: Studio Notebooks Numbered by Rattner, 1942-1968
  9.2: Studio Notebooks Chronologically Arranged, 1935-1975, undated
  - Studio Notebooks Numbered by Rattner, 1942-1968; 9.1
    - Record of work I, 1942-1946; (3 folders) (Box 10, Reel 5269)
    - Record of work II, 1947-1949 (Box 10, Reel 5269)
    - Record of work III, 1950-1952; (2 folders) (Box 10, Reel 5269)
    - Record of work IV, 1954-1956; (3 folders) (Box 10, Reel 5269-5270)
    - Record of work V, 1955-1960; (2 folders) (Box 10, Reel 5270)
    - Record of work VI, 1961-1962; (2 folders) (Box 10, Reel 5270)
    - Record of work VII, 1963-1964; (2 folders) (Box 10, Reel 5270)
    - Record of work VIII, 1965-1966; (2 folders) (Box 10, Reel 5270)
    - Record of work IX, 1967-1968; (3 folders) (Box 10, Reel 5270)
  - Studio Notebooks Chronologically Arranged, 1935-1975, undated; 9.2
    - Notebook, 1935, 1938-1939 (Box 10, Reel 5270)
    - Arts and Crafts Club, New Orleans, 1942 (Box 10, Reel 5270)
    - Pigment techniques, 1947 (Box 10, Reel 5270)
    - List of works delivered, 1947-1949 (Box 10, Reel 5270)
    - Woodstock panel, 1949 (Box 10, Reel 5270)
    - Various notes, [circa 1950s] (Box 10, Reel 5270)
    - Paris, [circa 1950s] (Box 10, Reel 5270)
    - Notebook, 1954; (2 folders) (Box 10, Reel 5270)
    - Notebook, 1955-1957 (Box 10, Reel 5270)
    - Notebook, 1956-1958 (Box 10, Reel 5270)
    - Notebook, 1957; (2 folders) (Box 11, Reel 5270)
    - Notebook, circa 1960s; (2 folders) (Box 11, Reel 5271)
    - Notebook, 1961-1962; (2 folders) (Box 11, Reel 5271)
    - Lithographs, prints, artist proofs, 1961-1975; (2 folders) (Box 11, Reel 5271)
    - Watercolor index, 1962-1963 (Box 11, Reel 5271)
    - Sag Harbor, [1965, 1967-1968] (Box 11, Reel 5271)
    - Israel, [1967-1968]; (2 folders) (Box 11, Reel 5271)
    - Outgoing artwork: gifts, exhibitions, 1967-1970 (Box 11, Reel 5271)
    - Outgoing artwork: Kennedy Gallery exhibition, 1968 (Box 11, Reel 5271)
    - Outgoing artwork: Heschels book Israel: An Echo of Eternity, [1970] (Box 11, Reel 5271)
    - Notebook, 1970-1975 (Box 11, Reel 5271)
    - Notebook, [1975]; (2 folders) (Box 11, Reel 5271)
    - Notebooks, undated; (10 folders) (Box 11, Reel 5271)
- Art Expenses, circa 1940-1970; Series 10; (boxes 11-13; 0.7 linear ft.)
  These files contain receipts for Rattner's art supplies. Some ledgers from the 1940s are included.
  Records are arranged chronologically by decade.
  - Art expenses, 1939-1950s; (5 folders) (Box 11, Reel 5271-5272)
  - Art expenses, 1945-1946; (ledger book) (Box 12 (hol), Reel 5272)
  - Art expenses, 1957-1970s; (4 folders) (Box 13, Reel 5272)
- Household Files, 1940-1970, undated; Series 11; (box 13; 0.8 linear ft.)
  This series is unfilmed. It includes apartment leases, stock certificates, insurance policies, and mortgage papers.
  - Household files, 1940-1970; (39 folders) (Box 13, Reel unfilmed)
- Financial Records, 1933-1963; Series 12; (boxes 13-14; 0.7 linear ft.)
  This series is unfilmed. It contains bank statements and canceled checks for accounts belonging to Abraham Rattner, Bettina Bedwell Rattner, and Esther Gentle Rattner. In addition, there are some bank statements from Esther Gentle Reproductions. The documents in this series are filed chronologically.
  - Financial records, 1933-1963; (12 folders) (Box 13, Reel unfilmed)
  - Financial records, 1933-1963; (22 folders) (Box 14, Reel unfilmed)
- Notes and Lists, 1936-1972, undated; Series 13; (box 14; 0.5 linear ft.)
  When possible, material in this series is filed chronologically, though most of the material is undated.
  - Lists of Rattner's paintings, 1936, undated (Box 14, Reel 5272)
  - Notes regarding Bettina Bedwell's sickness, 1947, undated (Box 14, Reel 5272)
  - Notes for Bettina Bedwell's funeral, 1947 (Box 14, Reel 5272)
  - Notes for New Modern Art Magazine, 1948 (Box 14, Reel 5272)
  - Miscellaneous notes and lists, 1950s-1970s, undated; (5 folders) (Box 14, Reel 5272)
  - Notes about camouflage, undated (Box 14, Reel 5272)
  - Miscellaneous notes, undated; (5 folders) (Box 14, Reel 5272)
  - Technical notes about lithograph, undated (Box 14, Reel 5272)
  - Notes about Allen Leepa, undated (Box 14, Reel 5272)
  - Notes referencing Leepa's book, Abraham Rattner, undated (Box 14, Reel 5272)
- Address Books, 1939-1977, undated; Series 14; (box 15; 1.0 linear ft.)
  The series contains address books belonging to Abraham Rattner and Esther Gentle Rattner.
  - Address books, 1939-1973, undated; (20 folders) (Box 15, Reel unfilmed)
- Date Books and Diaries, 1937-1977, undated; Series 15; (boxes 16-17; 1.6 linear ft.)
  The date books and diaries record the Rattners' daily lives, business appointments, and their personal thoughts. Most notable is Abraham Rattner's diary from 1939 recounting his departure from Paris to escape Nazism.
  This series has been divided into three subseries and filed chronologically:
  15.1: Abraham Rattner, 1937-1976, undated
  15.2: Abraham Rattner and Esther Gentle, 1955-1973, undated
  15.3: Esther Gentle, 1954-1977, undated
  - Abraham Rattner, 1937-1976, undated; 15.1
    - Date book/diary, 1937 (Box 16, Reel 5272)
    - Date book/diary, 1939 [1940] (Box 16, Reel 5272)
    - Date books/diaries, 1947-1949; (4 folders) (Box 16, Reel 5272)
    - Date books/diaries, 1954-1955 (Box 16, Reel 5272)
    - Date book/diary, 1955 (Box 16, Reel 5273)
    - Date books/diaries, 1958, 1959 (Box 16, Reel 5273)
    - Date books/diaries, 1962, 1966, 1967, 1974; (4 folders) (Box 16, Reel 5273)
    - Date book/diary, 1976 (Box 16, Reel 5273)
    - Date book/diary, undated (Box 16, Reel 5273)
  - Abraham Rattner and Esther Gentle, 1955-1973, undated; 15.2
    - Date books/diaries, 1955, 1956 (Box 16, Reel 5273)
    - Date book/diary, 1958 (Box 16, Reel 5273)
    - Date book/diary, 1964-1973 (Box 16, Reel 5273)
    - Date books/diaries, 1965-1960 (Box 16, Reel 5273)
    - Date books/diaries, undated (Box 16, Reel unfilmed)
  - Esther Gentle, 1954-1977, undated; 15.3
    - Date book/diary, 1954 (Box 17 (hol), Reel 5273)
    - Date book/diary, 1965, undated (Box 17 (hol), Reel 5273)
    - Date book/diary, 1972, undated (Box 17 (hol), Reel 5274)
    - Date book/diary, 1973 (Box 17 (hol), Reel 5274)
    - Date book/diary, 1977 (Box 17 (hol), Reel 5274)
- Scrapbooks, 1938-1952; Series 16; (boxes 18-22; 1.5 linear ft.)
  The disbound scrapbooks in this series record Rattner's professional life as an artist. Primarily, they contain clippings recording his exhibitions and professional achievements. The early scrapbooks also contain some correspondence, exhibition catalogs and announcements.
  - Scrapbook, 1938 (Box 18 (sol), Reel 5274)
  - Scrapbook, 1939 (Box 18 (sol), Reel 5274)
  - Scrapbook, 1941 (Box 18 (sol), Reel 5274)
  - Scrapbook, 1943-1945 (Box 19 (sol), Reel 5274)
  - Scrapbook, 1946 (Box 19 (sol), Reel 5274)
  - Scrapbook, 1947 (Box 20 (sol), Reel 5274)
  - Scrapbook, 1948 (Box 20 (sol), Reel 5274)
  - Scrapbook, 1949 (Box 21 (sol), Reel 5274)
  - Scrapbook, 1950 (Box 22 (sol), Reel 5274)
  - Scrapbook, 1952 (Box 22 (sol), Reel 5274)
- Printed Material, 1920s-1980s, undated; Series 17; (boxes 23-26; 3.6 linear ft.)
  This series contains exhibition catalogs, exhibition announcements for both Rattner and Gentle, clippings, and miscellaneous printed material that relates to Rattner. There is a large amount of unfilmed printed material that was collected by Rattner, but does not mention him. For a detailed list, see the Series Outline on page 10.
  - Exhibition catalogs for Rattner exhibitions, 1936-1986; (3 folders) (Box 23, Reel 5275)
  - Exhibition catalogs for group exhibitions with Rattner, 1944-1976, undated; (8 folders) (Box 23, Reel 5275)
  - Exhibition announcements, Abraham Rattner, 1930s-1970s, undated; (6 folders) (Box 23, Reel 5275)
  - Exhibition announcements, Esther Gentle, 1964-1965, undated (Box 23, Reel 5275)
  - Clippings, Abraham Rattner, 1930s-1950s, undated; (4 folders) (Box 23, Reel 5275)
  - Clippings, Abraham Rattner, 1950s-1980s, undated; (5 folders) (Box 24, Reel 5275)
  - Clippings, Abraham Rattner briefly mentioned, 1930s-1980s, undated; (9 folders) (Box 24, Reel 5275)
  - Clippings, Henry Miller, biographical material, 1930s-1980s, undated; (6 folders) (Box 24, Reel 5275)
  - Clippings, Henry Miller, writings, 1942, 1960s-1970s (Box 24, Reel 5275)
  - Clippings, Henry Miller, literary announcements and reviews, 1940s-1960s, undated; (4 folders) (Box 24, Reel 5275)
  - Clippings, advertisements for Rattner's exhibitions, 1940s-1970s (Box 24, Reel 5275)
  - Clippings, Abraham Rattner's art work, 1951-1978, undated; (2 folders) (Box 24, Reel 5275)
  - Clippings, Baghdad hangings, 1969-1970 (Box 24, Reel 5276)
  - Miscellaneous, pamphlets from Rattner's U.S.A. trip with Henry Miller, 1940 (Box 24, Reel 5276)
  - Miscellaneous, press releases, 1960s-1970s (Box 24, Reel 5276)
  - Miscellaneous, map of Israel showing Rattner's travel route, 1967 (Box 24, Reel 5276)
  - Miscellaneous, autograph book, 1969 (Box 24, Reel 5276)
  - Miscellaneous, art schools in which Rattner taught, undated (Box 24, Reel 5276)
  - Miscellaneous, catalogs about a film on Abraham Rattner, undated (Box 24, Reel 5276)
  - Exhibition catalogs not mentioning Rattner, 1944-1969; (3 folders) (Box 24, Reel unfilmed)
  - Exhibition catalogs not mentioning Rattner, 1971-1977, undated; (2 folders) (Box 25, Reel unfilmed)
  - Exhibition invitations and announcements not mentioning Rattner, 1920s-1980s, undated; (8 folders) (Box 25, Reel unfilmed)
  - Clippings about art and other artists, 1940s-1980s, undated; (9 folders) (Box 25, Reel unfilmed)
  - Paul Gauguin, 1921-1964, undated; (3 folders) (Box 25, Reel unfilmed)
  - Bettina Bedwell, 1928, 1938, undated; (4 folders) (Box 25, Reel unfilmed)
  - U.S.A. trip with Henry Miller, 1937-1940; (4 folders) (Box 25, Reel unfilmed)
  - Art schools, 1940s-1970s, undated; (1 folder) (Box 25, Reel unfilmed)
  - Religious material, 1940s-1980s; (1 folder) (Box 25, Reel unfilmed)
  - Camouflage, 1942; (1 folder) (Box 25, Reel unfilmed)
  - Advertisements for Esther Gentle Reproductions, 1949, 1960, 1981, undated; (1 folder) (Box 26, Reel unfilmed)
  - Art competitions, 1950s; (1 folder) (Box 26, Reel unfilmed)
  - Israel and Judaism, 1950s-1970s; (3 folders) (Box 26, Reel unfilmed)
  - Gallery guides, 1950s-1960s; (1 folder) (Box 26, Reel unfilmed)
  - Art associations and societies, 1950s-1980s; (1 folder) (Box 26, Reel unfilmed)
  - Allen Leepa, 1950, 1964, 1966, undated; (1 folder) (Box 26, Reel unfilmed)
  - John Howard Griffin, 1957; (1 folder) (Box 26, Reel unfilmed)
  - South Africa/Vietnam, 1965-1967; (1 folder) (Box 26, Reel unfilmed)
  - Royal Hunt of the Sun, 1965; (1 folder) (Box 26, Reel unfilmed)
  - Stained glass, 1967-1968; (1 folder) (Box 26, Reel unfilmed)
  - Bernard Zipkin, 1968; (1 folder) (Box 26, Reel unfilmed)
  - Art auction material, 1970s; (1 folder) (Box 26, Reel unfilmed)
  - Museums, 1976, 1981; (1 folder) (Box 26, Reel unfilmed)
  - Printed art work, various artists, undated; (4 folders) (Box 26, Reel unfilmed)
  - Instructional art books, undated; (1 folder) (Box 26, Reel unfilmed)
  - Postcards, undated; (1 folder) (Box 26, Reel unfilmed)
  - Information on various art media, undated; (2 folders) (Box 26, Reel unfilmed)
- Writings by Others, 1945-circa 1980, undated; Series 18; (box 26; 20 folders)
  The series primarily contains writings on Abraham Rattner, although there are three additional unfilmed writings on other topics at the end of the series.
  - "A Bodhisattva Artist" by Henry Miller, 1945 (Box 26, Reel 5276)
  - "The Rattner Portfolio or For God So Loved the World" by Henry Miller, 1957; (2 folders) (Box 26, Reel 5276)
  - "A Word About Abraham Rattner" by Henry Miller, 1965 (Box 26, Reel 5276)
  - "Abraham Rattner" by Allen Leepa, 1969 (Box 26, Reel 5276)
  - "Rattner Rebuttal" by Allen Leepa, 1979 (Box 26, Reel 5276)
  - "The Spirituality of Abraham Rattner" by Robert Henkes, circa 1980s (Box 26, Reel 5276)
  - Untitled, by unknown author, undated (Box 26, Reel 5276)
  - "Rattner" by Henry Miller, undated (Box 26, Reel 5276)
  - "Abraham Rattner" by Henry Miller, undated (Box 26, Reel 5276)
  - "A Painting If It Is Achieved At All, Is Done With The Help of God" by Henry Miller, undated (Box 26, Reel 5276)
  - "Abraham Rattner" by Henry Miller, undated (Box 26, Reel 5276)
  - "Abraham Rattner" by Allen Leepa, undated (Box 26, Reel 5276)
  - "On Rattner" by Henry Miller, undated (Box 26, Reel 5276)
  - "On Rattner" by Maurice Raynal, undated (Box 26, Reel 5276)
  - "Les Coulisses de la Jeuve Penture,", 1960 (Box 26, Reel unfilmed)
  - "The Group in Depth" by Helen Durken, [1965] (Box 26, Reel unfilmed)
  - "Israel: An Echo of Eternity" by Abraham Joshua Heschel, undated; (3 folders) (Box 26, Reel unfilmed)
- Photographs, 1891-1970s, undated; Series 19; (boxes 27-29; 1.6 linear ft.)
  The majority of the photographs are of Abraham Rattner alone or with family and friends. In addition, there are photographs of Rattner's travels, his first wife Bettina Bedwell and his second wife Esther Gentle, as well as works of art.
  The series is organized into eleven subseries:
  19.1: Abraham Rattner, 1918-1970s
  19.2: Studios, 1956, undated
  19.3: Exhibitions, 1950-1970s, undated
  19.4: Family, 1940s, undated
  19.5: Friends, 1929-1968, undated
  19.6: Travel, 1939-1947
  19.7: Bettina Bedwell, 1891-1947, undated
  19.8: Esther Gentle, 1928-1970s, undated
  19.9: Works of Art by Rattner, 1922-1970, undated
  19.10: Works of Art by Others, undated
  19.11: Miscellaneous, undated
  - Abraham Rattner, 1917-1970s, undated; 19.1
    Included in this series are photographs of Rattner as a young man, as as soldier in World War I, as a young art student, as well as in middle age and an older man. A few photographs show Rattner in his early Paris studio. There are many photographs of Rattner with Bettina Bedwell. Some photos show Rattner at work or with his works of art. There are also photographs of Rattner at exhibitions and in his studio. The photographs are arranged roughly in chronological order.
    - Rattner, 1917-circa 1920s (Box 27, Reel 5276)
    - Rattner, Paris studio, 1930s (Box 27, Reel 5276)
    - Rattner and Bettina Bedwell, circa 1930s-circa 1940s; (2 folders) (Box 27, Reel 5276)
    - Rattner, including photographs by Alfredo Valente, circa 1940s; (2 folders) (Box 27, Reel 5276)
    - Rattner and Bettina Bedwell, vacation, 1946 (Box 27, Reel 5276)
    - Rattner studio, Urbana, Illinois, [1953-1954] (Box 27, Reel 5276)
    - Rattner at Temple University Citation ceremony, 1954 (Box 27, Reel 5276)
    - Rattner at Aspen, Colorado Conference of Design, 1954 (Box 27, Reel 5276)
    - Rattner signing Illinois Portfolio, 1956 (Box 27, Reel 5276)
    - Rettner designing Chicago Loop Synagogue stained glass, 1958 (Box 27, Reel 5276)
    - Rattner, circa 1960s-circa 1970s (Box 27, Reel 5276)
    - Rattner in Paris, circa 1965 (Box 27, Reel 5276)
    - Rattner with Gaugin fresco, 1965 (Box 27, Reel unfilmed)
    - Rattner with Victory painting, 1967 (Box 27, Reel 5276)
    - Rattner, 1969 (Box 27, Reel 5276)
    - Rattner portraits, circa 1970s (Box 27, Reel 5276)
    - Rattner attending exhibitions, circa 1970s (Box 27, Reel 5276)
    - Rattner with works of art, undated (Box 27, Reel 5276)
    - Rattner, undated (Box 27, Reel 5276)
    - Rattner in Paris studio, undated (Box 27, Reel 5276)
    - Rattner in his studio, 1975, undated (Box 27, Reel 5276)
    - Rattner and Bettina Bedwell dinner, undated (Box 27, Reel 5276)
    - Rattner and Esther Gentle, 1952, undated (Box 27, Reel 5276)
  - Studio Photographs, 1956, undated; 19.2
    This subseries include photos of Rattner's Sag Harbor studio and his studio in France during the 1950s and 1960s.
    - Studio, Sag Harbor, [1956] (Box 27, Reel 5276)
    - Studio, Paris, undated (Box 27, Reel 5276)
  - Exhibition Photographs, 1950s-1970s, undated; 19.3
    Photographs of Rattner and others attending exhibitions of his work are found here. Exhibitions included are the Carnegie Institute; the Downtown Gallery; Corcoran Gallery of Art; the Kennedy Gallery; "...and there was light," an exhibition of Rattner's stainedglass designs for the Chicago Loop Synagogue; and photographs from the exhibition "Our America."
    - Carnegie Institute Painting in the United States, 1950 (Box 27, Reel 5276)
    - Carnegie Institute, Pittsburgh International, 1950 (Box 27, Reel 5276)
    - Metropolitan Museum of Art, American Water Colors, Drawings and Prints, 1952 (Box 27, Reel 5276)
    - Downtown Gallery, 1960 (Box 27, Reel 5276)
    - Unidentified exhibition, undated; (2 folders) (Box 27, Reel 5276)
    - Corcoran Gallery of Art, Alexander Calder and Abraham Rattner exhibition, undated (Box 27, Reel 5276)
    - Kennedy Gallery exhibition, undated (Box 27, Reel 5276)
    - And There Was Light, studies for the Chicago Loop Synagogue, circa 1970s (Box 27, Reel 5276)
    - UNESCO and UN, World on View, undated (Box 27, Reel 5276)
    - Our America, undated (Box 27, Reel 5276)
  - Family, 1940s, undated; 19.4
    An index of photographs taken by Rattner in 1946 is included here. Many of the photos mentioned in this index were taken during Rattner and Bedwell's trip to California in 1946. This subseries also contains photos of Rattner's family, including an undated photograph of his father, his brothers and sisters and their families, and photographs of the families of Bettina Bedwell and Esther Gentle.
    - Family photographs, 1941-1946; (4 folders) (Box 27, Reel 5276)
    - Index to photographs taken by Rattner, 1946 (Box 27, Reel 5276)
    - Rattner and Bettina Bedwell's trip, 1946; (2 folders) (Box 27, Reel 5276)
    - Family, 1946; (3 folders) (Box 27, Reel 5276)
    - Family, 1956, 1964-1965, undated; (3 folders) (Box 27, Reel 5276)
    - Family, undated; (4 folders) (Box 27, Reel 5276)
  - Photographs of Friends, 1929-1968, undated; 19.5
    This subseries includes photographs of Henry Miller, Joan Miro, Richard de Rochemont, Weeks Hall, John Dos Passos, and Kay Boyle.
    - Friends, 1929 (Box 27, Reel 5276)
    - Henry Miller, 1940-1943, undated (Box 27, Reel 5276)
    - Rattner, Dick de Rochemont, Bettina Bedwell, 1930, undated (Box 27, Reel 5276)
    - Joan Mirot, Juan Mirot, and daughter, 1936 (Box 27, Reel 5276)
    - Weeks Hall, 1921 [1941] (Box 27, Reel 5276)
    - Friends, 1930s (Box 27, Reel 5276)
    - John Dos Passos, 1930s, 1941 (Box 27, Reel 5276)
    - Friends, 1940, undated (Box 27, Reel 5276)
    - U.S.A. trip, Anais Nin, 1941 (Box 27, Reel 5276)
    - U.S.A. trip, Rattner, Weeks Hall, Henry Miller, circa 1941 (Box 27, Reel 5276)
    - René Lefebore Foinet and Bettina Bedwell, 1946 (Box 27, Reel 5276)
    - Unidentified friends, undated; (3 folders) (Box 27, Reel 5276)
    - Jim Stinybooch and Judith, undated (Box 27, Reel 5276)
    - Rattner and Esther Gentle with unidentified couple, undated (Box 27, Reel 5276)
    - Jack Lawrence with Louis Rattner, 1968 (Box 27, Reel 5276)
    - Rattner, Bettina Bedwell, Kay Boyle, undated (Box 27, Reel 5276)
    - Rattner, Esther Gentle, Russel Cowles, James T. Sweeney at de Crieft birthday party, undated (Box 27, Reel 5276)
    - Rattner and Bettina Bedwell with unidentified people, undated (Box 27, Reel 5276)
    - William Kienbusch, undated (Box 27, Reel 5276)
  - Travel Photographs, 1939-1947; 19.6
    This small subseries of photographs include photos of Rattner and Bedwell during their trip to London in 1939-1940, scenery from Rattner and Bedwell's trip to California via train in 1946, and photographs from Rattner's trip from Nevada City, California to New York with Armand and Suzie d'Usseau in 1947.
    - Rattner and Bettina Bedwell trip to London, circa 1939-1940 (Box 27, Reel 5276)
    - Rattner and Bettina Bedwell trip to western United States, 1946, undated; (2 folders) (Box 27, Reel 5276)
    - Vacation scenery, 1946 (Box 27, Reel 5276)
    - Cross-country trip with Armand and Suzie d'Usseau, 1947 (Box 27, Reel 5276)
  - Bettina Bedwell, 1891-1947, undated; 19.7
    Rattner kept many photographs of his first wife, such as a photograph of Bedwell when she was two years old, photos entitled "When We First Met," as well as formal portraits and snapshots from the 1930s and 1940s.
    - Bettina Bedwell with family and friends, 1891, circa 1920s-1947; (11 folders) (Box 27, Reel 5276)
  - Esther Gentle, 1928-1970s, undated; 19.8
    Photographs of Rattner's second wife of almost 30 years include an early photograph of Gentle and her three young sons dated 1928 and photographs of Gentle and Rattner in her studio.
    - Esther Gentle, 1928, 1963, circa 1970s, undated; (4 folders) (Box 27, Reel 5276)
  - Works of Art by Rattner, 1922-1970, undated; 19.9
    Most of Rattner's work is represented in this group of black and white photographs. They were used for documentation purposes, to keep track of which paintings were sent to galleries and exhibitions.
    - Photographs of artwork, 1922-1970s; (13 folders) (Box 27, Reel 5276-5277)
    - Photographs of artwork, undated (Box 28 (hol), Reel 5277)
    - Sketches from U.S.A. trip with Henry Miller, undated (Box 28 (hol), Reel 5277)
    - Photographs of paintings, undated (Box 28 (hol), Reel 5277)
    - Negative of Chicago Loop Synagogue stained glass window, undated (Box 28 (hol), Reel unfilmed)
  - Works of Art by Others, undated; 19.10
    A few photographs of works of art by others are included in the collection. This subseries is unfilmed
    - Works of art by others, undated; (4 folders) (Box 28 (hol), Reel unfilmed)
  - Miscellaneous, undated; 19.11
    This subseries is unfilmed and includes fashion photographs that once belonged to Bettina Bedwell, scenes from Beggar's Opera, and photographs of the Joan d'Arc fresco painted by Paul Gaugin.